{"tossups": [{"question": "According to legend, Henry I died by eating too much of this food. The Scania market featured a Hanseatic League monopoly on this food. The United Kingdom and Iceland fought a so-called war over one type of this food. Garum was a Roman sauce made from these animals, which are harvested off the Grand Banks of Newfoundland. For ten points, name these animals, a primary food source in Scandinavia, that can be caught with a net or rod and reel.", "answer": "<b> fish</b> (accept<b> lamprey</b>s, salt<b> fish</b>,<b> herring</b>,<b> cod</b>,<b> fish</b> sauce, or any other type of fish)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man ordered the building of a torture chamber with a beautiful exterior, known as his \u201chell.\u201dThis man\u2019s son, Mahinda, was sent on a proselytizing mission, and this man had the Mahabodhi Temple built. This ruler built a structure, currently located in the Sarnath Museum, which is topped by four lions; that column is inscribed with this man\u2019s moral edicts. For ten points, name this grandson of Chandragupta Maurya, a devout Buddhist convert who ruled India in the 3rd century BC.", "answer": "<b> Ashoka</b> the Great", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Soldiers attacking this capital city during Operation Danube were deceived into thinking they were operating against fascist elements. In protest of human rights abuses, Jan Palach set himself on fire in this city\u2019s Wenceslas Square. A meeting in this city led to the the removal of Antonin Novotny as First Secretary and the ascension of Alexander Dub\u02d8cek [doob-check], who began a series of liberalizing reforms. For ten points, identify this namesake of a 1968 \u201cSpring\u201d uprising against Communism, the capital of Czechoslovakia.", "answer": "<b> Prague</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Description acceptable. In 2003, the University of Washington fired football coach Rick Neuheisel [nu-hi-zel] for engaging in this activity. An open challenge to complete this process perfectly for a one billion dollar prize was instituted in 2014 by Warren Buffett. President Obama has been criticized for his\u201cchalk\u201d in this process, which he does on an annual ESPN special called Barack-etology. For ten points, name this annual activity of attempting to predict the results of a premier college basketball tournament.", "answer": "filling out a<b> bracket</b> for the<b> NCAA</b> men\u2019s basketball<b> tournament</b> (accept equivalent descriptions, including<b> March Madness</b> in place of \u201cNCAA tournament\u201d; prompt on gambling; prompt on partial answers) Page 1", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This body of water names Joshua Barney\u2019s flotilla of barges that fought in the Battle of Bladensburg. For almost a century until the 1950s, pirates fought a ban on dredging mollusks in this bay in the \u201cOyster Wars.\u201d The Comte de Grasse defeated the British in a 1781 battle at the mouth of this bay, which is fed by the York and Susquehanna Rivers and traversed by a bridge-tunnel that connects the Hampton Roads area to the Delmarva Peninsula. For ten points, name this large bay that is shared by Virginia and Maryland, the largest estuary in the United States.", "answer": "<b> Chesapeake</b> Bay", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Tsali led attacks on federal soldiers during this event. Winfield Scott was ordered to start this event and allowed John Ross, a member of the Treaty Party, to supervise it. The legal basis for this event, the Treaty of New Echota, was signed by Major Ridge after a gold rush in Dahlonega [duh-LAW-nuh-ga], Georgia. For ten points, name this forced relocation of the Cherokee, Seminole, and other Native American tribes during the 19th century.", "answer": "<b> Trail of Tears</b> (accept descriptions of \u201cthe removal of Native Americans from their land\u201duntil \u201cNative American\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "When this man was transferred to Temple Number 7 in Harlem in 1954, his prot\u00b4eg\u00b4e Louis Farrakhan replaced him in Boston. This man controversially claimed that the assassination of JFK represented\u201cchickens coming home to roost and claimed that violence may be necessary in the \u201cBallot or the Bullet\u201d speech. For ten points, name this civil rights leader, a critic of Martin Luther King, Jr., who was assassinated in 1965 after leaving the Nation of Islam.", "answer": "<b> Malcolm X</b> (or el-Hajj Malik el-<b>Shabazz</b>; accept Malcolm<b> Little</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This state\u2019s \u201cjungle primaries\u201d allow political parties to list multiple candidates. In 2016, David Duke announced his candidacy for this state\u2019s Senate seat. John Bel Edwards was elected governor of this state in 2015, succeeding the term-limited incumbent, Bobby Jindal. In summer 2016, FEMA declared disaster areas in 20 of this state\u2019s parishes. For ten points, name this Southern U.S. state where August 2016 flash flooding devastated the capital, Baton Rouge.", "answer": "<b> Louisiana</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This artistic medium was historically manufactured on the island of Murano in Venice. Dale Chihuly primarily works in this medium, which was used to create four pyramids for the courtyard of the Louvre by I.M. Pei. A colored type of this medium was used by Louis Comfort Tiffany for a series of ornate lamps, as well as in the windows of Chartres Cathedral. For ten points, identify this sand-based artistic medium, often used in \u201cstained\u201d windows.", "answer": "<b> glass</b> (accept blown<b> glass</b>, stained<b> glass</b>, etc.) Page 2", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This ruler was succeeded in one of his territories by Robert Curthose and required all landowners to pledge their loyalty via the Salisbury Oath. This ruler conducted the Harrying of the North and landed at Pevensey to begin an invasion. The compilation of the Domesday Book [\u201dDoomsday Book\u201d] survey was ordered by this leader, who defeated a king who had just won the Battle of Stamford Bridge. For ten points, name this leader who became King of England after winning the Battle of Hastings.", "answer": "<b> William the Conqueror</b> (or<b> William I</b> of England; accept<b> William II of Normandy</b> or <b>William the Bastard</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "During this man\u2019s Presidency, John Fries launched a rebellion against the taxes that this man used to build a navy. This man attempted to pack the judiciary with the Midnight Judges, leading to the case<em> Marbury v. Madison</em>. Upon losing the Election of 1800, this man peacefully ceded power to Thomas Jefferson. For ten points, name this second president of the United States.", "answer": "<b> J</b>ohn<b> Adams</b> (prompt on Adams; do not accept John Quincy Adams)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "At this venue on New Years Eve 1989, David Hasselhoff performed his hit song<em> Looking for Freedom</em>. This location was home to<em> My God, Help Me To Survive This Deadly Love</em>, a depiction of Brezhnev and Honecker embracing, in its East Side Gallery. Due to poor grammar, John F. Kennedy awkwardly claimed to be a donut after this structure was built, and Ronald Reagan appealed to \u201cMr. Gorbachev\u201d to tear it down. For ten points, name this structure that fell in 1989, reuniting the German capital city.", "answer": "<b> Berlin Wall</b> (or<b> Berliner Mauer</b>; prompt on Berlin before \u201cstructure\u201d is said)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {}, {"question": "In this empire, people or land could be granted a form of quasi-sovereignty called immediacy. In 1500, this empire was reformed into a series of six Circles, including the Swabian Circle. This empire\u2019s rulers included Henry IV, who feuded with Gregory VII during the Investiture Controversy, and a ruler who defeated the Magyars at Lechfeld. Otto the Great led, for ten points, what patchwork of states located in modern-day Germany, whose emperor was crowned by the Pope in Rome?", "answer": "<b> Holy Roman</b> Empire (accept<b> HRE</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The<em> Amagi</em> was scrapped in this city\u2019s drydock after it suffered extensive damage in an earthquake centered just southwest of this city at Sagami Bay. A fire tornado killed tens of thousands of people in this city during the aforementioned 1923 earthquake, which failed to destroy the Imperial Hotel, built by an American architect. The 1923 Great Kanto earthquake devastated, for ten points, what city on the island of Honshu, the capital city of Japan?", "answer": "<b> Tokyo</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "Dorgon oversaw the ascension of this dynasty. The Hundred Days\u2019 Reforms and the Self-Strengthening Movement were attempts to modernize under this dynasty. It required its subjects to wear their hair in a queue and divided its military into the Eight Banners. An empress of this dynasty, Cixi [tsee-chee], supported the anti-western Boxer Rebellion. For ten points, name this dynasty that ruled China from 1648 to 1911, the last imperial dynasty.", "answer": "<b> Qing</b> Dynasty (accept<b> Manchu</b> Dynasty)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "The Ringle Report opposed this policy, which was implemented under John DeWitt at facilities like Tule Lake and Manzanar. 1942\u2019s Executive Order 9066 instituted this policy, whose constitutionality was upheld in the Supreme Court decision<em> Korematsu v. United States</em>. John DeWitt testified that \u201cAmerican citizenship does not necessarily determine loyalty\u201d in support of, for ten points, what policy in which over 100,000 Asian-Americans were forcibly detained in camps during World War II?", "answer": "<b> internment of Japanese</b>-Americans", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This structure was restored by the Fossati brothers during the reign of Abdulmecid. The \u201cwishing column\u201d in this structure has been allegedly moist ever since 1200 when</b> <b>it was visited by Thaumaturgus. This structure contains the Deesis (+)</b> <b>mosaic, as well</b> <b>as mosaics dedicated to Empress Zoe and John II Comnenus. Isidore of Miletus designed this structure, which is famous for a \u201cdome of light\u201d effect created by forty windows. This structure\u2019s name means (*)</b> \u201cHoly Wisdom,\u201d and it was commissioned by Justinian I. For ten points, name this Orthodox basilica in Constantinople.", "answer": "<b> Hagia Sophia</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Edwin Guthrie, a researcher in this school of thought, formulated a \u201cone-trial theory\u201dthat opposed its founders\u2019 findings. The Premack Principle in this school of thought was</b> <b>tested on children using gumballs and pinball machines. Edward (+)</b> <b>Thorndike, an early</b> <b>proponent of this school of thought, devised his Law of Effect by observing cats figure out puzzle boxes. Working within this school of thought, John (*) </b> Watson and B. F. Skinner theorized \u201cclassical\u201d and \u201coperant\u201d types of conditioning. For ten points, name this school of psychology which focuses on quantifiable changes in a person\u2019s actions.", "answer": "<b> behaviorism</b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s law is a statement of Georges Lema\u02c6\u0131tre\u2019s [le-MET\u2019s] observation that distant galaxies are Doppler shifted to indicate movement away from Earth. A mathematical</b> <b>formulation of that law involves a (+)</b> <b>constant, also named for this man, whose inverse is</b> <b>approximately the age of the universe. In 1925, this astronomer used Cepheid [SEH-fee-id] variables to estimate the distance to M31, (*) </b> Andromeda, one of numerous nebulae shown to actually be galaxies by this man. For ten points, name this American astronomer who was honored as the namesake of a NASA space telescope launched in 1990.", "answer": "Edwin<b> Hubble</b> (accept<b> Hubble</b> (Space) Telescope) Page 9", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>A speech by this man ends by noting \u201cGod\u2019s work must truly be our own\u201d and warns that America will \u201cpay any price, bear any burden\u201d to assure \u201cthe success of liberty.\u201d This</b> <b>man \u201chappens also to be a (+)</b> <b>Catholic\u201d according to a campaign speech shortly before</b> <b>he became the first Catholic U.S. (*)</b> President. For ten points, name this American president who proclaimed \u201cask not what your country can do for you; ask what you can do for your country\u201d in his inaugural address in 1960.", "answer": "<b> J</b>ohn Fitzgerald<b> Kennedy</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This country antagonized a neighbor via the Hallstein Doctrine, a brief policy of breaking diplomatic relations with countries that officially recognized that neighbor. Foreign agents within this country sponsored the far-left (+) Red Army Faction, which was co-founded by Andreas Baader. This country tried to improve relations with its neighbor via</b><em><b> ostpolitik</b></em><b>, as supported by (*)</b> Willy Brandt. This country was divided into British, American, and French zones via an agreement at the Yalta conference. For ten points, name this European country that, in 1990, re-united with its eastern neighbor.", "answer": "<b> West Germany</b> (or<b> Federal Republic of Germany</b> or<b> FRG</b>, do not prompt on Germany alone) Page 10", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}